Register of the Edward Geary Lansdale papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Edward Geary Lansdale papers
1910-1987
80116
Hoover Institution Archives
93 manuscript boxes, 5 oversize boxes, 244 envelopes, 1 oversize folder, 5 album boxes, 2 slide boxes (65.0 linear feet)
Writings, memoranda, reports, studies, correspondence, printed matter, sound recordings, and photographs relating to the Vietnam War and to counter-guerrilla operations, especially in Vietnam and the Philippines.
Lansdale, Edward Geary, 1908-1987
Access
Collection is open for research.
Use copies of some sound recordings, video recordings, or motion picture material in this collection are available for immediate access. To access other sound recordings, video recordings, or motion picture material, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1980.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1908 February 6 Born, Detroit, Michigan.
1942-1945 Served with the O.S.S.
1943 Promoted to Lieutenant, U.S. Army. Served in military intelligence for duration of war.
1945-1948 Promoted to Major. Transferred to Philippines, AFWESPAC. Appointed Chief of Intelligence Division. Extended stay in Philippines at AFWESPAC and PHILRYCOM; helped Philippine Army rebuild its Intelligence Services.
1947 Commissioned as a Captain in the Air Force, temporary rank of Major.
1948 Instructor, Strategic Intelligence School, Lowry Air Force Base, Colorado.
1949 Temporary promotion to Lieutenant Colonel.
1950 At the request of President Elpidio Quirino, transferred to Joint U.S. Military Advisory Group in the Philippines to advise Philippine Army Intelligence Services in fight against the Huks (Communists). Met Ramon Magsaysay, Philippine Secretary of National Defense; became close friends. Assisted in development of psychological operations, civic actions, rehabilitation of Huk prisoners, and other programs.
1951 Temporary promotion to Colonel.
1953 Member of General J. W. "Iron Mike" O'Daniel's mission to the French forces in Indochina; acted as an advisor on special counter-guerrilla operations.
1954-1956 Transferred to Saigon, served with MAAG-Vietnam. Helped advise Vietnamese government and armed forces on problems of internal security, including pacification program (1954-55), psychological operations, intelligence, and integration of sect armies. Became close associate of President Ngo Dinh Diem.
1957 Went to office of the Secretary of Defense, Washington, D.C.; became Deputy Assistant Secretary for special operations.
1959 Staff member of President's Committee on Military Assistance (Draper Committee).
1960 Temporary promotion to Brigadier General.
1961 Became Assistant Secretary of Defense for special operations.
1963 Temporary promotion to Major General.
1963 October 31 Retired; awarded Distinguished Service Medal (second time) for counter-insurgency work. Became consultant to director of Food for Peace, White House.
1965-1967 Returned to South Vietnam as Senior Liaison Officer of the U.S. Mission to South Vietnam, appointed by Ambassador Henry Cabot Lodge. Also appointed Minister by President Johnson. Staff became the "Senior Liaison Office" (SLO). Work involved winning support in Vietnamese countryside.
1967-1968 Assistant to Ambassador Ellsworth Bunker, U.S. Mission to South Vietnam.
1972 Author, In the Midst of Wars.
1987 February 23 Died, McLean, Virginia.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Lansdale papers are drawn almost entirely from the post-World War II period and consist of writings, memoranda, reports, studies, correspondence, printed matter, sound recordings, and photographs relating to the Vietnam War and to counter-guerrilla operations, especially in Vietnam and the Philippines..
The first five series (Biographical File, Correspondence, Diaries and Notebooks, Speeches and Writings, and Subject File) consist of materials drawn from 1945-1987. The diaries record some of Lansdale's impressions and experiences during his first period in the Philippines. Within the Speeches and Writings series are the notes and drafts for Lansdale's memoirs (In the Midst of Wars), containing material not published in the final version. The Subject File series is very broad, but of special interest under "Vietnam" are the sub-headings "politics and government" and "Republic of Vietnam." The latter is a sampling of memoranda and other papers from the government of Ngo Dinh Diem and his successors. Finally, several pamphlets outlining "operational guidelines" for cadre working within the rural construction (revolutionary development) program are found under "Vietnamese conflict" (sub-heading "pacification").
The next five series follow Lansdale's career paths from his first years in the Philippines to his last stay in Vietnam. There are three very compact series of material from his two periods in the Philippines and his first period in Vietnam. The bulk of the collection is found in the other two career series: the files from the Department of Defense, Office of the Secretary of Defense, and from the United States Embassy-Saigon, Senior Liaison Office.
In the Department of Defense series are found memoranda, reports, and other items from the Draper Committee, including schedules from that committee's 1959 tour of some Southeast Asia countries. Notes, correspondence, and comments from Lansdale's 1961 trip to Vietnam (with General Maxwell Taylor's party) are also of interest and are found in this series under "subject file" (sub-heading "Vietnam").
Within the Senior Liaison Office series, the "day files" are especially complete (except for the security withdrawals--see below). These files comprise a record of each outgoing letter, memo, and report. Because of the sensitive nature of many of the Lansdale papers, there have been many documents withdrawn for security reasons. In the place of these documents the researcher will find numbered out cards. These documents are reviewed for declassification consideration at five-year intervals, and those that have been returned to the collection can be found in the Declassified Documents series.
Other series include oversize materials, printed matter, audiovisual material, maps and charts, and memorabilia. The various sound recordings collected by Lansdale may be of especial interest to researchers.
Guerrilla warfare.; Guerrillas--Philippines.; Guerrillas--Vietnam.; Philippines.; Phonotapes.; Slides (Photography).; United States--Armed Forces.; United States. Air Force--Officers.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Vietnam.
- Biographical File, 1910-1986
  Scope and Contents note
  Appointment calendars, invitations, identification papers, materials relating to career (such as promotion letters, awards, and orders), family papers, clippings and articles by others about Lansdale, and information on the collection itself, arranged alphabetically by subject or form.
  - General, miscellany (Box 69)
  - Appointment calendars, 1967-1968
  - Awards, certificates, citations
  - Biographical sketches
  - Clippings and articles, 1949-1986
  - Consulting agreements (Box 70)
    - Braddock, Dunn and McDonald, Inc., 1972-1981
      Correspondence and mimeograph outline entitled "Threat Assessment."
    - C.A.C.I., 1979
      Letter, contract, and mimeograph entitled "A Coding System for Deception."
  - Financial records
  - Identification cards and permits, Saigon
  - Insurance and medical papers
  - Invitations, tickets, programs
  - Lansdale family
    - General, genealogical material
    - Lansdale, Helen Bacheller
    - Lansdale, Henry
  - Memoranda
    Includes material relating to Lansdale's connection with the Central Intelligence Agency (CIA).
  - Military service records
  - Military service records (Box 71)
  - Sketches by Lansdale, 1967
  - Unpublished writings by others [see also: CORRESPONDENCE/May, Gary and Currey, Cecil]
    - Hewet, Robert, "Major General Edward Geary Lansdale,", 1965 October 22
    - Kushner, Rose, "The Quiet American Comes Home," and "The Quiet American Returns to Vietnam,", circa 1967
- Correspondence, 1934-1987
  Personal and family correspondence, mainly from the years following Lansdale's service in Vietnam as Senior Liaison Officer (post-1968), with a few items from earlier years, arranged alphabetically by correspondent.. Official correspondence, and non-official correspondence mailed to Lansdale at one of his offices, may be found under the appropriate office file series.
  - General
    - Unidentified, 1936-1986 (Box 1)
    - Alphabetical
      - General, 1939-1987
      - Vietnamese correspondents, 1969-1986
    - Recommendations, 1969-1983 (Box 2)
  - Air Force Association, 1961-1981
  - Aldridge, Elden, 1971-1973
  - All-American Conference to Combat Communism, 1965
  - Allen, Edward W., 1972
  - Allen, Gary, 1975
  - Allen, Thomas E., Jr., 1975
  - Alvarado, Lorenzo, 1972-1974
  - American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations, 1977
  - American Society for Industrial Security, 1964
  - Anderson, B. L., 1979
  - Anderson, Dillon, 1959-1973
  - Armstrong, Hamilton Fish, 1968
  - Arellano, Oscar, 1971-1973
  - Arundel, Arthur W., 1972-1978
  - Bachman-Beck, Milicent F., 1977-1986
  - Baird, James C. and Mary, 1973-1979
  - Banzon, Joseph, 1969-1974
  - Beaven, Sky, 1972-1974
  - Benge, Mike, 1974-1978
  - Black, Ed, 1970-1984
  - Bodry, Ira T., 1970
  - Bohannan, Charles T. and Dorothy, 1972-1983
  - Braim, Paul F., 1969
  - Brandt, Carol, 1968-1978
  - Britton, Edward C., 1980
  - Broger, John C., 1979
  - Broun, Heywood, 1934
  - Brown, David E., 1968
  - Buell, Thomas B., 1972-1973
  - Buerger, Max, 1971
  - Bui Anh Tuan, 1975-1981
  - Bui Ngoc Phuong, undated
  - Bunker, Ellsworth, 1969
  - Burns, Robert J., 1969-1986
  - Byers, Marge, 1971
  - Can, Pham Duy [see: Pham Duy Can]
  - Carson, Betty, undated
  - Carter, Thomas, 1983
  - Chase, Walter P., 1972-1975
  - Chau, Nguyen Van [see: Nguyen Van Chau]
  - Choate, Charlie, 1975-1977
  - Chowe, Stephen H., 1969-1978
  - Clark, Dale, 1968-1974
  - Clark, Helen, undated
  - Cohen, Martin A., 1969
  - Colby, William, 1982-1986
  - Conlon, John, 1972-1974 (Box 3)
  - Connolly, M. W., 1973-1975
  - Contemporary Authors (New York), 1978
  - Cooke, Charles, 1969-1982
  - Cooke, Dwight, 1969
  - Cooperative Forum, Inc., 1965
  - Cramer, Thomas K., 1970
  - Critchfield, Richard, 1968-1972
  - Currey, Cecil, 1984-1985
  - Dang Van Sung and family, 1975-1976
  - Dang, Joseph Nguyen Phoc, 1975-1983
  - DeJaegher, Father Raymond J., 1962-1980
  - Douglas, James H., 1973
  - Drinnon, Richard, 1979
  - Droge, Dolf, 1968-1969
  - Dupuy, T. N., 1978
  - Eddy, Gould L., 1972-1986
  - Edwards, William M., 1976
  - Ellsberg, Daniel, 1972
  - Far East Luncheon Group, Washington, D.C., 1979
  - Fensterward, Bernard, 1970
  - Fishel, Wesley R., 1970
  - Fisher, Thomas L. [see also: SUBJECT FILE/Bolt, Beranek, and Newman, Browne and Shaw International Studies Division], 1969
  - Fraleigh, Bert, 1970-1985
  - Freedoms Foundation at Valley Forge, 1965-1980
  - Fricelli, Joseph J., undated
  - Frivaldo, Juan G., 1978-1985
  - Gallery, Father John I., 1969-1979
  - Garrettson, Chuck, 1984-1986
    Includes writings by Garrettson.
  - Gillingham, Peter, 1968-1978
  - Gober, Hershel [see also: SOUND RECORDINGS], 1977-1978
  - Gold, Bill, 1970
  - Goldberg, Sherwood D., 1974
  - Goodman, Allan E., 1974
  - Grinter, Lawrence E., 1975
  - Hamilton, Alexander, 1979-1984
  - Harper and Row, Publishers, 1970
  - Harriman, W. Averell, 1977
  - Hay, J. H., 1970
  - Herrington, Stu, 1979-1982
  - Herz, Martin F., 1969
  - Hilbert, Philip F., 1973-1974
  - Hingher, W. H., 1969-1972
  - Ho Quang Phuoc, 1968-1986
  - Ho, Vu Ngoc [see: Vu Ngoc Ho]
  - Hoa, Nguyen Lac [see: Nguyen Lac Hoa]
  - Hoai, Le Khac [see: Le Khac Hoai]
  - Hoffer, Tom W., 1971-1974
  - Holland, Paul, 1972-1986
  - Hoover Institution, 1968-1986 (Box 4)
  - Hradel, Joseph R., 1972-1980
  - Hull, Ron, 1971
  - Humphrey, Hubert H., 1971-1975
  - Hurley, Alfred F., 1971-1979
  - Huss, Mark, 1969-1985
  - Jackson, Andrew D., 1973-1986
  - Jacqueney, Theodore and Victoria, circa 1971-1979
    Includes eulogies for Theodore Jacqueney.
  - James, Daniel V., 1977-1986
  - Johnson (Lyndon Baines) Library, 1979
  - Jonker, Frederick, 1977-1985
  - Jordan, Amos A., 1969
  - Justiniano, Medardo T., 1980-1985
  - Karnow, Stanley, 1978
  - Karrick, Samuel N., 1968-1979
  - Kelly, Patrocinio (Mrs. Edward Lansdale), 1972-1973
  - Kennedy (John F.) Library, 1973-1979
  - Keovimol, Watana [see also: Tiro, Hasan Muhammad di], 1976
  - Kiem, Pham Huy [see: Pham Huy Kiem]
  - Kissinger, Henry A., 1972
  - Knowlton, William, 1972
  - Komer, Robert W., 1971
  - Kosutic, Peter, 1969-1972
  - Knaus, John Kenneth, 1978
  - Kushner, Rose, 1970-1984
  - Labin, Suzanne, 1972
  - Ladejinsky, Wolf, 1959
  - Lalwani, Sheila, 1979
  - Lam, Tran Van [see: Tran Van Lam]
  - Lansdale family, 1972-1984 (Box 82)
  - Lansdale, Benjamin and Eleanor, 1967-1985
  - Lansdale, David, 1976-1987
  - Lansdale, Edward G., 1955-1979 (Box 83)
  - Lansdale, Edward R., 1956-1985
  - Lansdale, Ethel Dow, 1947
  - Lansdale, Gayle, 1976
  - Lansdale, Godfrey A., 1966
  - Lansdale, Helen, 1946-1966
  - Lansdale, Henry, 1953
  - Lansdale, John, 1971-1986
  - Lansdale, Patrocinio [see: Kelly, Patrocinio (Mrs. Edward Lansdale)]
  - Lansdale, Phil and Jean
    - 1960-1977
    - 1978-1987 (Box 84)
  - Lavin, Greg, 1973-1984 (Box 5)
  - Le Khac Hoai, 1960-1985
  - Le Phuoc Sang, 1978
  - Leighton, Richard M., 1971
  - Leonard, Jerris, 1979
  - Loye, John F., Jr., 1971
  - McArthur, George, undated
  - McLean, Donald H., 1963-1977
  - Magsaysay, Jesus, 1977
  - Magsaysay, Luz, 1972-1977
  - Maik, Angelina S., 1978
  - Mallin, Jay, 1971-1974
  - Marcos, Ferdinand, 1974
  - Marr, David G., 1969-1970
  - Martin, David, 1971-1974
  - May, Gary, 1977-1979
  - Mehlert, Calvin and Nguyet, 1968-1986
  - Melvin, George H., 1966-1980
  - Menton, William, 1983-1985
  - Miller, Hank, 1968-1980
  - Miskovish, Reggie, 1970-circa 1978
  - Mojica, Proc, 1978
  - Morgan, Edward P., 1969
  - Morse, Brad, 1970
  - Moskin, J. Robert, 1969
  - Moss, William, 1978
  - Muni, Donald Stuart, undated
  - Muni, Steven D., 1976
  - Napier, John H. and Cameron, 1977-1984
  - National Defense Council (F. Andy Messing), 1984-1986
  - Navarro, Ed, 1964-1983
  - Nedelcovic, Bosco, 1975
  - New York Times (Herbert Mitgang), 1972-1973
  - Ngo Dinh Nhu, Madame, 1974
  - Nguyen Duc Thang, 1968-1975
  - Nguyen Lac Hoa, 1968
  - Nguyen Tat Ung, Mrs., undated
  - Nguyen Thai and Mai, 1964-1986
  - Nguyen Van Chau, 1978-1984
  - Nguyen Van Thuong, 1975-1983
  - Nhu, Madame Ngo Dinh [see: Ngo Dinh Nhu, Madame]
  - Nhut, Trinh Minh [see: Trinh Minh Nhut]
  - Nixon for President Committee, 1968 (Box 6)
  - Nixon, Richard, 1957-1984
  - Nolte, Richard, 1971
  - Nurse, Ronald J., 1976
  - Ocampo, Galo B., 1979-1980
  - O'Daniel, John W., 1972-1973
  - Orendain, John C., 1970-1972
  - Pageant (New York), 1969
  - Pamintuan, Manuel, 1978
  - Peet, Richard, 1975-1984
  - Pham Duy Can, 1975-1980
  - Pham Huy Kiem, 1976
  - Pham Van Lieu and family, 1973-1975
  - Phan Quang Dan, 1981-1986
  - Phillips, Rufus, 1971-1979
  - Phuoc, Ho Quang [see: Ho Quang Phuoc]
  - Phuong, Bui Ngoc [see: Bui Ngoc Phuong]
  - Pia, Anthony, 1972-1983
  - Picher, Oliver S., 1974
  - Pierce, Russell K., 1971
  - Pollard, Eric W., 1968-1979
  - Potebnya, Orr Y., 1968-1984
  - Praeger, Frederick A., 1961-1979
  - Pratt, John Clark, 1982-1985
  - Quigg, Philip W., 1969
  - Qurino, Carlos, 1981
  - Richards, Peter C., 1960-1986 (Box 7)
  - Richardson, Gilbert P., 1975
  - Roberts, Hu, 1979-1986
  - Rosson, William B., 1977-79
  - Rockefeller, John D., III, 1974-1975
  - Russ, Martin, 1976
  - Russei, Chester, undated
  - Sabin, L. S., 1972
  - Sadler, Jack, 1975-1976
  - Salyers, W. Keith, 1970
  - San Juan, Frisco F., 1972
  - San Miguel, Eloisa Litonjua, 1978
  - Sang, Le Phuoc [see: Le Phuoc Sang]
  - Schlesinger, Arthur, Jr., 1976-1977
  - Scott, William L., member of Congress, 1971
  - Seagrave, Sterling, 1986
  - Shaplen, Robert M., 1972-circa 1975
  - Sharpe, Larry, 1972-1983
  - Shelley, Robert K., 1975
  - Simpson, Paul, 1969-1970
  - Smith, H. Morgan, 1977
  - Soldier of Fortune, 1975
  - Staar, Richard F., 1972-1980
  - Stilwell, Richard G., 1978-1986
  - Stoneman, Steven, 1972-1976
  - Story, Edward C., 1970
  - Stuber, Paul, 1979
  - Sullivan, Thomas W., III, undated, 1977
  - Sweet, Charles F., 1969, 1971
  - Swing, John Temple, 1968
  - Thai, Nguyen [see: Nguyen Thai]
  - Thang, Nguyen Duc [see: Nguyen Duc Thang]
  - Thien, Ton That [see: Ton That Thien]
  - Time (New York), 1970
  - Tiro, Dara, 1978
  - Tiro, Hasan Muhammad di [see also: SUBJECT FILE/Indonesia/Tiro, Hasan Muhammad di], 1960-1979
  - Ton That Thien, 1977-1983
  - Tordella, Louis W., 1962-1976
  - Torelli, Fred, 1976-1980
  - Tran Ngoc Chau and family, 1979-1980
  - Tran Van Do, 1980
  - Tran Van Lam, 1969-1984
  - Trinh Minh The and family, 1969-1986 (Box 8)
  - Truscott, Lucian K., 1975
  - Tuan, Bui Anh [see: Bui Anh Tuan]
  - Tugwell, Rexford, 1972-1973
  - Turner, Alvin C., 1971
  - Turner, Stansfield, 1979
  - Ung, Mrs. Nguyen Tat [see: Nguyen Tat Ung, Mrs.]
  - United States Military Academy, 1972-1986
  - U.S. News and World Report, 1979-1986
  - United States. Air Force, 1968-1986
  - United States. Army, 1973-1984
  - United States. Army. Institute for Military Assistance, 1976
  - United States. Department of Defense, 1972-1985
  - United States. Library of Congress, 1972-1979
  - United States. Marine Corps, 1982
  - United States. Navy, 1985
  - University of Hawaii, 1968
  - Valentine, Don, 1983-1984
  - Valenzona, Ben S., 1969-1973
  - Vance, Cyrus, 1977-1978
  - Villamor, Manette M. and family, 1978-1984
  - Vu Ngoc Ho, 1969
  - Vondra, Sharon M., 1970
  - Wachtel, Jack, 1968-1975
  - Walls, Lester R., 1975-1981
  - Ward, W. T. T. (Chips), 1957-1983
  - Westmoreland, W. C., 1968-1975
  - Whitlow, Robert H., 1971
  - White, Peter, 1964-1986
  - White, Philip, 1976
  - Williams, Ogden, 1978
  - Williams, Samuel T., 1972-1983
  - Wilson, Samuel N., 1972-1979
  - Wolf, Charles, Jr., 1968-1982
  - Wolff, Lester L., member of Congress, 1971
  - Yepez, Cefferina, 1972-1986
  - Young Americans for Freedom, 1979
- Diaries and Notebooks, 1941-1956 (Box 72)
  Diaries written in the Philippines and Vietnam, arranged chronologically [see also: CORRESPONDENCE/Lansdale, Helen].
- Speeches and Writings, 1954-1984
  Lectures, talks, panel discussions, articles, and drafts, including all drafts of Lansdale's memoirs, In the Midst of Wars, arranged alphabetically by title. Additional speeches and writings are found in the Department of Defense series.
  - General (Box 73)
    - Bound volumes of collected works
    - Correspondence, 1968-1985
    - Miscellaneous drafts and notes (Box 74)
  - "After the War, Still Vietnam," New York Times, typescript, printed copy, and letters, 1972 September 5
  - "The American Revolution," typescript memorandum, 1973 February 6
  - "The American Spirit," typescript memorandum, 1972 October 13
  - "Art of Guerrilla," The Christian Science Monitor, printed copy, 1964 January 18
  - "Binh Hung: A Counter-Guerrilla Case Study," mimeograph, 1961 February 1
  - "A Case History of Insurgency--The Philippines," speech, the National War College, typescript, 1964 March 26
  - "A Catalyst Team for Vietnam," mimeograph, 1964 June 12
  - "The Challenge of Subversive Insurgency," speech, Michigan State University, holograph, program, letters, and miscellany, 1964 February 29
  - "Civic Action," speech, Counter-Guerrilla School, Special Warfare Center, Fort Bragg, North Carolina, mimeograph, 1961 February 24
  - "Civic Action Helps Counter the Guerrilla Threat," Army Information Digest, printed copy, 1962 June
  - "Civil Activities of the Military, Southeast Asia," memorandum, mimeograph, 1959 March 13
  - "Communist Insurgency," speech, American Society for Industrial Security, holograph and typescript, 1964 September
  - "A Comparison: Viet Nam and the Philippines," unpublished paper, typescript, undated
  - "Comrades," Bulletin of the American Historical Collection, typescript, letter, and printed copy, 1984 April-June
  - "Concept for Victory in Vietnam," mimeograph and notes, 1964 June 8
  - "The Early Involvement, 1945-1961," typescript and letters, 1979
    Memorandum relating to a manuscript by Ronald Spector.
  - "Early Years: Vietnam," lecture, Army War College, holograph, 1977 March 22
  - "The Electoral Process in Vietnam," Washington Post, printed copy, 1971 August 31
  - "Eulogy for Oscar Arellano," typescript, 1974 November 9
  - "The Free Citizen in Uniform," speech, U.S. Army Civil Affairs School, Fort Gordon, Georgia, mimeograph, 1960 November 1
  - "Freedom Academy," unpublished paper, Washington, D.C., typescript, 1965 June
  - "Freedom and Democracy: A Declaration of Principles," unpublished paper, mimeograph, 1961 October 3
  - "Fundamentals for Americans," speech, Military Government Association, Shoreham Hotel, Washington, D.C., mimeograph, 1959 June 13 (Box 75)
  - "General Lansdale on Vietnamese Elections," Washington Post, typescript, printed copy, and clippings, 1971 May 26
  - "General Lansdale Replies," Washington Post, typescript, printed copy, and clipping, 1972 September 12
  - "General Plan for SEA Study 1954-64," unpublished paper, mimeograph, undated
  - "Get to the People With a Better Idea," printed copy, 1965 August 29
  - "Guerrilla Warfare: Lessons Learned and Their Implications," speech notes, Council on Foreign Relations, New York, holograph, 1964 April 13
  - "How to Win in Vietnam," typescript, 1965 January 10
  - "In the Midst of War: Folk Music, Viet Nam, 1965-1967," typescript, undated
  - In the Midst of Wars, 1972
    - General
      - Correspondence [see also: CORRESPONDENCE/Brandt, Carol]
        - General, 1968-1984
        - Harper and Row, 1968-1973
      - Excerpts - Clippings from a Vietnamese newspaper
      - Reviews
    - Draft, holograph
    - Draft, holograph (Box 76)
    - Notes, typescript and holograph
    - Comments on draft, typescript and holograph
    - Comments on draft, typescript
    - Draft, holograph (Box 77)
    - Draft, chapters covering experiences in Philippines, typescript
    - Draft, chapters covering experiences in Philippines and trip, typescript, 1953 (Box 78)
    - Draft, chapters covering experiences in Vietnam, typescript
    - Draft, annex for back of book section, typescript
    - Draft, typescript
  - "Individual re the State," holograph, 1957 February 19 (Box 79)
  - "The Insurgent Battlefield," speech, Air Force Academy, mimeograph, 1962 May 25
  - Interview, printed copy, undated
  - Interview, transcript and letters by Joe Treaster, 1975
  - Interview, Lyndon Baines Johnson Library oral history project, transcripts and correspondence, 1981 June-September
  - Interview, Library of Congress, transcript and letter, 1982 November 19
  - Interview, Journal of Defense and Diplomacy, printed copy, 1983 July
  - Interview, Honolulu Star-Bulletin, printed copy, 1984 January 7
  - Interview, U.S. State Department, transcript and letters, 1984 September 6
  - "Introduction...U.S. Organization for the War," typescript, undated